Today we're going to look at five
essential items you need to create
luxury ice cream in your home ice cream
[Music]
machine. Yeah. So ice cream is all about
science. It's not just to throw this and
that into a pot and hope for the best.
But there are some things that you
should have at home in your kitchen, in
your pantry, wherever it might be to
really help you create the best ice
cream you can. So today, let's go
through those five essential items that
you
need. The first one is skimmed milk
powder. Depending on whereabouts in the
world you are, this can be called zero
fat milk powder, ultra lowfat milk
powder. This is not whole milk powder.
Whole milk powder has a really weird
taste and when you put it in ice cream,
it changes the flavor of whatever it is.
So, skim milk powder, which is basically
zero taste outside of that of milk, is
essential because what it does, it
increases the solids of your ice cream
base and mimics what commercial ice
cream makers do when they pasteurize.
When you pasteurize, you increase the
temperature, allows evaporation, which
then increases your solids. That is what
that does. You can get this from
anywhere. your supermarkets. In the UK,
you can get this from Sainsburries,
Tesco's, Aldi, Little, whatever. In
Canada, you can get this in real
Canadian supertore. You can get this in
Safeways, Walmart. Actually, my local
Walmart hasn't had it for ages, but you
can literally you can literally get this
anywhere. The next essential item you'll
need
is some kind of invert sugar.
Now, that could either be corn syrup. If
you're one of those people that hates
using corn syrup, then you can get
straight glucose syrup. You could use
honey. You could use maple syrup or
designated invert sugar. All of these
are essentially very, very similar. And
what they do, invert sugar creates a
unique texture and mouth feel and ice
cream that is basically impossible to
mimic without using it. So, use one of
those in the same numbers that my
recipes tell you to and you'll be
good. The third essential item you need
for luxury ice cream making is dextrose.
This is also called corn sugar in North
America. It can also be called brewer
sugar in the UK and Europe. I think you
can also call it brew sugar in the US as
well. It's the same thing. All of these
names, it's the same thing. Dextro will
reduce the freezing point. So, you can
have an ice cream that is really easy to
scoop straight out of the freezer. This
is essential if you want to take your
Ninja
recipes up a level, even more so with
the Ninja Swirl. Because if you make a
really hard ice cream, it's going to
struggle to come out of there. Now, if
you create an ice cream that spins
really nicely, it will come out of your
ninja swell much more appropriately. So,
dextrose corn sugar. You cannot buy this
in supermarkets. You have to go to you
can buy on Amazon. You can buy in
brewery shops, wine making shops,
anything like this. There's four or five
wine making businesses in Calgary. So
that's where I go and get that. It comes
in larger bags, usually about 2 kilos in
size. So that 2 kilo bag super cheap,
but it will last you probably an entire
year. The next essential item is some
kind of thermometer, something to read
temperature. Whether that is a candy
thermometer, a laser thermometer, a
sugar thermometer specifically,
whatever, doesn't make any difference.
You need to make sure that your ice
cream base temperature is correct when
you're cooking it off. If you're just
guessing when it starts to create steam,
so evaporation starts to happen, that
happens at around 55° centigrade all the
way up to boiling point and beyond. So
there is no way to determine what your
temperature is without the means to
measure it. Amazon 10 bucks. Perfect.
Get yourself one of these. The final
essential item you need for ice cream
is
scales. Now obviously a lot of my
viewers are in the US. So
hi. You guys love your cups. that's what
you've become accustomed to using over
the years. There are some things that it
just doesn't work for. Some things will
Let's just look at flour for instance.
You can pack flour into a cup and it
weighs different than if you don't pack
it or if you just pack it slightly less.
These things have a really critical
impact on your ice cream if you use
cups. So, if you really want to go that
next level, start weighing your
ingredients. baking as a whole. Uh, and
that encompasses, you know, like ice
cream and scientific based
recipes, you need scales to measure
those out. There's no way you're going
to use teaspoons to really accurately
measure out a stabilizer if that's
something that you use. So, obviously,
these scales are way too big for a
stabilizer. So, if you are going to use
a stabilizer, then I recommend you get a
little set of these. These are sometimes
called jeweler scales or micro scales.
Amazon, less than $10. And that will
really help you take your ice cream
right up to the next level. The final
thing, this isn't essential, this is a
special mention, is stabilizers.
Stabilizers have got a bad rap over the
years because of how they've been used.
They've been misused by bulk
manufacturers to create some really
weird products. But ultimately you can
get guar gum which is processed from
beans from the gua tree. It's really
clean. It it's about as clean label
stabilizer as you're going to get and it
will really help create longevity. So
you go through all the effort of making
your delicious luxury ice cream and it
just doesn't last. Looking at those with
the ninja creamies, the ninja swirls,
start looking at something like guar
gum. It will really really help your ice
cream texture over a period of time. And
there's nothing worse than I mean there
are lots of things worse, but in the
world of ice cream, there's nothing
worse than going into the freezer and
taking a tub out and it's just started
turning to ice after a few days. That is
a a pretty crappy recipe, but b the
likelihood is there isn't a stabilizer
in there. Add that stabilizer and that
ice cream will be perfect for weeks and
weeks and weeks.
All it does is absorb water. That is all
it does. Okay? Doesn't do anything
crazy. It doesn't break scientific law.
It just absorbs water. That ice that
gets created is just excess water that
hasn't been dealt with. The stabilizer
just absorbs that and keeps it in a
matrix within your ice cream. So, a
super easy, nice video. Five essential
items you need for luxury ice cream
making at home. I am gonna start
changing the way I make my videos for
YouTube. I am going to start reducing
the length much less chat and I'm going
to be putting scientific explanations on
Patreon and for YouTube members as well.
So if you are interested in the science
of ice cream, become a YouTube member or
head over to Patreon. There are links in
the description. There are links at the
end of the video. And you can ask me any
questions you have related to my YouTube
videos. But other than that, I will see
you next week when we get back to making
ice cream.
[Music]